<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2015 ForgeRock AS.
  !
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-basic-install'
         xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
         version='5.0'
         xml:lang='en'
         xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
         xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook
                             http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
         xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'>

 <title>Getting Started With OpenIDM</title>

 <!-- The suggestion was "Understanding OpenIDM", but that misses the point
 of the chapter. I could split this chapter into two, but this chapter
 is already pretty short to begin with. -->

 <para>
  Whenever you need access to important information, administrators need to
  know who you are. They need to know your identity, which may be distributed
  in multiple accounts.
 </para>

 <itemizedlist>
  <para>
   As a user, you might have several accounts even within your own company,
   for functions such as:
  </para>
  <listitem>
   <para>Email</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>Human Resources</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>Payroll</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>Engineering, Support, Accounting, and other functions</para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>

 <para>
  Each of these accounts may be stored in different resources, such as
  Active Directory, OpenDJ, OpenLDAP, and more. Keeping track of user
  identities in each of these resources (also known as data stores) can get
  complex. OpenIDM can simplify the process, as it reconciles differences
  between resources.
 </para>

 <para>
  With situational policies, OpenIDM can handle situations such as a missing
  or updated address for a specific user. OpenIDM includes default but
  configurable policies to handle such conditions. In this way,
  OpenIDM ensures consistency and predictability in an otherwise-chaotic
  resource environment.
 </para>

 <para>
  OpenIDM can make it easier to track user identities across these
  resources. OpenIDM has a highly scalable, modular, readily deployable
  architecture that can help you manage workflows and user information.
 </para>

 <section xml:id="gsg-what-openidm-cando">
  <title>What Can You Do With OpenIDM?</title>

  <para>
   With OpenIDM, you can simplify the management of identity, as it can
   help you synchronize data across multiple resources. Each organization
   can maintain control of accounts within their respective domains.
  </para>

  <para>
   OpenIDM works equally well with user, group, and device identities.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can also configure workflows to help users manage how they sign up for
   accounts, as part of how OpenIDM manages the life cycle of users and their
   accounts.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can manage employee identities as they move from job to job. You will
   make their lives easier as OpenIDM can automatically register user accounts
   on different systems. Later, OpenIDM will increase productivity when it
   reconciles information from different accounts, saving users
   the hassle of entering the same information on different systems.
  </para>

 </section>

 <section xml:id="gsg-learning">
  <title>What You Will See In This Document</title>

  <para>
   In this guide, you will see how OpenIDM reconciles user data between two data
   stores. We will look at a department that is adding a third engineer,
   Jane Sanchez.
  </para>

  <para>
   Your Human Resources department has updated their data store with Jane
   Sanchez's information. You want to use OpenIDM to update the internal
   Engineering data store. But first, you have to start OpenIDM.
  </para>

 </section>

 <section xml:id="before-you-start">
  <title>What You Need Before Starting OpenIDM</title>

  <para>
   This section covers what you need to have on your system before running
   OpenIDM.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>Operating System</literal>: Windows or UNIX/Linux.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>Java</literal>: Java Runtime Environment (JRE) Standard Edition
     (Java SE) 7, update 6 or later, or Java 8. Alternatively, you can use the
     same version of the Java Development Kit (JDK). On Linux, you may also
     install the OpenJDK package native to your updated Linux distribution.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     At least 150 MB of free disk space.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     At least 1 GB of free RAM.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     If your operating system includes a firewall, make sure that it allows
     traffic through (default) ports 8080 and 8443.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <section xml:id="java-prerequisites">
   <title>Java Environment</title>
<!--   <indexterm>
    <primary>Java</primary>
    <secondary>Requirements</secondary>
   </indexterm> -->
   <para>
    On Windows systems, after installing Java, set the
    <literal>JAVA_HOME</literal> environment variable. To do so on Windows 7,
    take the following steps:
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para>
      Locate your JRE or JDK installation directory. For a default installation of
      Java 8 on Windows 7, you should find the directory here:
      <literal>C:\Program Files\Java\jre-<replaceable>version</replaceable></literal>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select Server Manager &gt; Local Server &gt; Computer Name to open a
      System Properties window.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Select Advanced &gt; Environment Variables.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Set the value of <literal>JAVA_HOME</literal> to match the
      JRE or JDK installation directory.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </section>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="download-and-start">
  <title>Downloading and Starting OpenIDM</title>

  <procedure xml:id="download-start-openidm">

   <para>
    This procedure assumes that you are downloading and starting OpenIDM
    as a regular (not administrative) user named <literal>user</literal>.
   </para>

   <!-- After discussion with Mark, I'll revise the noted chapter the
    what's in comments for the release of OpenIDM 4.0.0. For now, we have
    no choice. -->

   <step>
    <para>
     Download the OpenIDM binary package,
     <filename>openidm-${docTargetVersion}.zip</filename>. Navigate to the
     <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://forgerock.org/openidm/"
      ><citetitle>ForgeRock Community</citetitle></link> page, and select
     <literal>Unstable Nightly Builds</literal>.
    </para>
    <!-- As requested by marketing -->
    <para>
     For more information on the contents of the OpenIDM binary package, see
     the following appendix of the Integrator's Guide:
     <link xlink:show="new" xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
           xlink:href="integrators-guide#appendix-file-layout">
      <citetitle>File Layout</citetitle></link>.
    </para>
    <note>
     <para>
      There are risks with any unstable build. When the next version of
      OpenIDM is released, ForgeRock will revise this section to point to the
      stable enterprise build, which will be available from
      <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="https://backstage.forgerock.com/#!/downloads">
       <citetitle>ForgeRock Backstage</citetitle></link>.
     </para>
    </note>
   </step>

   <!--
   <step>
    <para>Download the OpenIDM binary package,
     <filename>openidm-4.0.0.zip</filename>. Navigate to the
     <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://forgerock.org/openidm/"
      ><citetitle>ForgeRock Community</citetitle></link> page, and select
     <literal>Stable Enterprise Builds</literal>.
    </para>

    <para>Enterprise downloads are tested, stable releases.</para>
   </step>                            -->

   <step>
    <para>
     Extract the contents of the OpenIDM binary file to your user's
     <filename>Downloads</filename> directory. The process should unpack the
     contents of OpenIDM to the <filename>Downloads/openidm</filename>
     subdirectory.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Navigate to the <filename>Downloads/openidm</filename> subdirectory.
    </para>
    <stepalternatives>
     <step>
      <para>
       In Microsoft Windows, use Windows Explorer to navigate to the
       <literal>C:\Users\<replaceable>user</replaceable>\Downloads\openidm</literal>
       directory.
      </para>
      <para>
       Double-click the <filename>getting-started(.bat)</filename> file.
       Do not select the <filename>getting-started.sh</filename> file, as
       that is intended for use on UNIX/Linux systems.
      </para>
<!-- I'd like to include a screenshot of the Windows console here, but
      that would reveal a warning, ref OPENIDM-3445 -->
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       In Linux/UNIX, open a command line interface and run the following
       commands:
      </para>
      <screen>$ <userinput>cd /home/user/Downloads/openidm</userinput>
$ <userinput>./getting-started.sh</userinput></screen>
     </step>
    </stepalternatives>
    <para>
     In both cases, the script starts OpenIDM with a group of configuration
     and data files appropriate for users who need a quick introduction to
     OpenIDM. You will also see a warning about a password not being defined
     in the CSV file (<literal>WARN Password attribute is not defined.
     [CSVFileConfiguration]</literal>). You can ignore this warning.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     When OpenIDM is ready, you will see the following message:
    </para>
    <screen>-&gt; OpenIDM ready</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>
   Once OpenIDM is ready, you can administer it from a web browser. To do so,
   navigate to <literal>http://localhost:8080/admin</literal> or
   <literal>https://localhost:8443/admin</literal>. If you have
   installed OpenIDM on a remote system, substitute that hostname or IP
   address for <literal>localhost</literal>.
  </para>

  <note>
   <para>
    ForgeRock recommends that you connect to OpenIDM via the default secure
    port, 8443, and import a signed certificate into the OpenIDM truststore,
    as discussed in
    <link xlink:show="new" xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
          xlink:href="integrators-guide#security-management-service">
     <citetitle>Accessing the Security Management Service</citetitle>.
    </link>
   </para>
   <para>
    Until you install that certificate, you will see a warning in your browser
    at least the first time you access OpenIDM over a secure port.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   The default username and password for the OpenIDM Administrator is
   <literal>openidm-admin</literal> and <literal>openidm-admin</literal>.
  </para>

  <mediaobject>
   <alt>The OpenIDM Web Console</alt>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/gsg-openidm-login.png" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>
   When you log into OpenIDM at a URL with the <literal>/admin</literal>
   endpoint, you are logging into the OpenIDM Administrative User Interface,
   also known as the Admin UI.
  </para>

  <para>
   The first time you log in as the OpenIDM Administrator, OpenIDM prompts
   you to change your password. Do so. Note how OpenIDM requires a relatively
   complex password. You can change password policies as described in the
   OpenIDM Integrator's Guide chapter on
   <link xlink:show="new" xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
         xlink:href="integrators-guide#chap-passwords"><citetitle>Managing
   Passwords</citetitle></link>.
  </para>

  <mediaobject>
   <alt>Change Your Administrative Password</alt>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/gsg-password.png" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

 </section>

 <section xml:id="gsg-data-files">
  <title>The Getting Started Data Files</title>

  <para>
   In a production deployment, you are likely to see resources like
   Active Directory and OpenDJ. But the setup requirements for each
   are extensive, and beyond the scope of this document.
  </para>

  <para>
   For simplicity, this guide uses two static files as data stores:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <filename>hr.csv</filename> represents the Human Resources
     data store. It is in CSV format, commonly used to share data
     between spreadsheet applications.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <filename>engineering.xml</filename> represents the Engineering
     data store. It is in XML format, a generic means for storing complex
     data that is commonly used over the Internet.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   You can find these files in the OpenIDM binary package that you
   downloaded earlier, in the following subdirectory:
   <filename>openidm/samples/getting-started/data</filename>.
  </para>
 </section>

 </chapter>