<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2015 ForgeRock AS.
  !
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-openidm-demo'
         xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
         version='5.0'
         xml:lang='en'
         xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
         xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook
                             http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
         xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'>
 <title>Reconciling Identity Data</title>

 <para>
  Now that you have installed OpenIDM with a "Getting Started" configuration,
  you will learn how OpenIDM reconciles information between two data stores.
 </para>

 <para>
  While the reconciliation demonstrated in this guide uses two simplified
  data files, you can set up the same operations at an enterprise level on
  a variety of resources.
 </para>

 <para>
  Return to the situation described earlier, where you have Jane Sanchez
  joining the engineering department. The following illustration depicts what
  OpenIDM has to do to reconcile the differences.
 </para>

 <mediaobject>
  <alt>OpenIDM can reconcile differences between data stores</alt>
  <imageobject>
   <imagedata fileref="images/gsg-recon-top.png" format="PNG"/>
  </imageobject>
 </mediaobject>

 <section xml:id="data-files">
  <title>Using OpenIDM to Reconcile Differences</title>

  <para>
   A central feature of OpenIDM is reconciliation. In other words, OpenIDM can
   compare the contents of two data stores, and make decisions on what to do,
   depending on the differences.
  </para>

  <para>
   This scenario is based on two data files:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para><filename>hr.csv</filename>, which represents the Human Resources
    data store</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para><filename>engineering.xml</filename>, which represents the
    Engineering data store</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   OpenIDM will modify the Engineering data store by adding the newly hired
   Jane Sanchez. As suggested by the following illustration, it will also
   address detailed differences between Jane's Human Resources account and
   the Engineering data store.
  </para>

  <mediaobject>
   <alt>Data Stores have different categories of data</alt>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/gsg-differences.png" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>
   OpenIDM includes configuration files that map detailed information from
   the Human Resources data store to the Engineering data store.
   For example, the OpenIDM configuration maps the <literal>firstName</literal>
   entry in Human Resources to the <literal>firstname</literal> entry in
   Engineering.
  </para>

  <note>
   <para>
    Mapping between data stores may require additional configuration. You should
    find two <filename>provisioner.openicf-*.json</filename> files in the
    <filename>/path/to/openidm/samples/getting-started/conf</filename>
    subdirectory. It is one way you can set up
    <link xlink:show="new"
          xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
          xlink:href="integrators-guide#chap-resource-conf">
    <citetitle>Connections to External Resources</citetitle></link>, such as
    Active Directory, OpenDJ or even the <filename>engineering.xml</filename>
    and <filename>hr.csv</filename> files used in this guide.
   </para>
  </note>

  <para>
   In the Admin UI, you can see how OpenIDM reconciles the different
   categories for user Jane Sanchez. Log into the Admin UI at
   <literal>https://localhost:8443/admin</literal>. The default username is
   <literal>openidm-admin</literal> and default password is
   <literal>openidm-admin</literal>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Select Mappings &gt; <literal>HumanResources_Engineering</literal> &gt;
   Properties.
  </para>

  <para>
   In the Sample Source text box, type in <literal>Sanchez</literal>. You
   should see a drop-down entry for Jane Sanchez that you can select.
   You should now see how OpenIDM would reconcile Jane Sanchez's entry
   in the Human Resources data store into the Engineering data store.
  </para>

  <mediaobject>
   <alt>OpenIDM can reconcile differences for Jane Sanchez</alt>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/gsg-recon-details.png" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>
   Scroll back up the same page. Select Reconcile Now.
  </para>

  <para>
   When you reconcile the two data stores, OpenIDM will make the change to
   the Engineering data store.
  </para>

  <para>
   For those of you who prefer the command line interface, you can see how
   the mapping works in the <filename>sync.json</filename> file, in the
   <filename>/path/to/openidm/getting-started/conf</filename> directory.
  </para>

 </section>

 <section xml:id="gsg-try-one-change">
  <title>Reconciling Identity Data After One Update</title>

  <para>
   Now that you have used OpenIDM to reconcile two data stores, try something
   else. Assume the Engineering organization wants to overwrite all user
   telephone numbers in its employee data store with one central telephone
   number.
  </para>

  <para>
   For this purpose, you can set up a default telephone number for the next
   reconciliation.
  </para>

  <para>
   In the HumanResources_Engineering page, scroll down and select
   <literal>telephoneNumber</literal> &gt; Default Values.
  </para>

  <mediaobject>
   <alt>Set a New Default Telephone Number</alt>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/gsg-telephone.png" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>
   When you select Update, and Save Properties, OpenIDM changes the
   <filename>sync.json</filename> configuration file. The next time OpenIDM
   reconciles from Human Resources to Engineering, it will include that
   default telephone number for all employees in the Engineering group.
  </para>
 </section>

 </chapter>