<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! legal/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2012 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-best-practices'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
 version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>OpenIDM Project Best Practices</title>
 <indexterm>
  <primary>Best practices</primary>
 </indexterm>

 <para>This chapter lists points to check when implementing an identity
 management solution with OpenIDM.</para>

 <section xml:id="immplementation-phase">
  <title>Implementation Phases</title>

  <para>Any identity management project should follow a set of well defined
  phases, where each phase defines discrete deliverables. The phases take
  the project from initiation to finally going live with a tested
  solution.</para>

  <section>
   <title>Initiation</title>
   <para>The project's initiation phase involves identifying and gathering
   project background, requirements, and goals at a high level. The deliverable
   for this phase is a statement of work or a mission statement.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
   <title>Definition</title>
   <para>In the definition phase, you gather more detailed information on
   existing systems, determine how to integrate, describe account schemas,
   procedures, and other information relevant to the OpenIDM deployment.
   The deliverable for this phase is one or more documents that define
   detailed requirements for the project, and that cover project definition,
   the business case, use cases to solve, and functional specifications.</para>

   <variablelist>
    <para>The definition phase should capture at least the following.</para>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>User Administration and Management</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>Procedures for managing users and accounts, who manages users,
      what processes look like for joiners, movers and leavers, and what is
      required of OpenIDM to manage users</para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Password Management and Password Synchronization</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>Procedures for managing account passwords, password policies,
      who manages passwords, and what is required of OpenIDM to manage
      passwords</para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Security Policy</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>What security policies defines for users, accounts, passwords, and
      access control</para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Target Systems</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>Target systems and resources with which OpenIDM must integrate.
      Information such as schema, attribute mappings and attribute
      transformation flow, credentials and other integration specific
      information.</para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Entitlement Management</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>Procedures to manage user access to resources, individual
      entitlements, grouping provisioning activities into encapsulated
      concepts such as roles and groups</para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Synchronization and Data Flow</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>Detailed outlines showing how identity information flows from
      authoritative sources to target systems, attribute transformations
      required</para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Interfaces</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>How to secure the REST, user and file-based interfaces, and to
      secure the communication protocols involved</para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Auditing and Reporting</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>Procedures for auditing and reporting, including who takes
      responsibility for auditing and reporting, and what information is
      aggregated and reported. Characteristics of reporting engines provided,
      or definition of the reporting engine to be integrated.</para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Technical Requirements</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>Other technical requirements for the solution such as how to
      maintain the solution in terms of monitoring, patch management,
      availability, backup, restore and recovery process. This includes any
      other components leveraged such as a ConnectorServer and plug-ins for
      password synchronization on Active Directory, or OpenDJ.</para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section>
   <title>Design</title>
   <para>This phase focuses on solution design including on OpenIDM and other
   components. The deliverables for this phase are the architecture and design
   documents, and also success criteria with detailed descriptions and test
   cases to verify when project goals have been met.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
   <title>Build</title>
   <para>This phase builds and tests the solution prior to moving the solution
   into production.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
   <title>Production</title>
   <para>This phase deploys the solution into production until an
   application steady state is reached and maintenance routines and procedures
   can be applied.</para>
  </section>
 </section>
</chapter>
